<chapter id="ch-basic-api">

	<title>Basic API</title>

	<section id="sect-eboxglobal">
		<title><classname>EBox::Global</classname></title>

		<para>The <classname>EBox::Global</classname> class offers various
		module management functions. The most commonly used functions are those
		regarding module instantiation. <classname>EBox::Global</classname>
		works as a module factory, you get an instance of it using the
		<methodname>getInstance</methodname> static method and then you can use
		that instance to create modules. The factory comes in two flavors, a
		read-only flavor and a read-write one.</para>

		<para>Calling <methodname>getInstance</methodname> without arguments
		will yield a read-write factory, which creates modules that let
		you make calls which change the configuration. A very important
		detail of read-write modules is that they return their latest
		configuration information, even if it has not been saved (which
		means that it could be revoked later by the user). This idea is
		important, configuration info reported by a read-write module
		should not be treated as final, unless that module has no changes
		waiting to be saved. You can see if a module has unsaved changes
		by calling the <methodname>modIsChanged</methodname> method in the
		<classname>EBox::Global</classname> class.</para>

		<para>The idea behind the read-write modules behavior is to make it
		easy to build a configuration front-end. For example, if the user
		creates a new network object in the objects module, the new object will
		show up instantly in the firewall configuration, so he can create new
		firewall rules that use it. After all the desired changes have been
		made, the user saves the configuration. If he decides to cancel the
		changes he just made, both the new object and the firewall rules will
		be deleted.</para>

		<para>There is one situation when you don't want to get information
		that has not been saved yet. That's when you are generating the
		configuration file for a daemon, setting up firewall rules, setting
		the address for a network interface, or any other activity that
		needs the real, final configuration info. This situation happens
		in system scripts (the boot script, cron jobs, etc). In these
		cases you need what we call read-only modules, they only report
		saved information and they do not allow method calls that change
		the configuration of the module. To obtain read-only modules you
		create <classname>EBox::Global</classname> instance setting its
		<parameter>readonly</parameter> parameter to <literal>true</literal>.
		Module instances returned by a factory created in this way will be
		read-only ones. This script shows how to get an instance of the squid
		module and tell it to restart itself:</para>

		<example>
			<title>Creating a read-only module instance</title>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[#!/usr/bin/perl

use strict;
use warnings;

use EBox;
use EBox::Global;
use Error qw(:try);

EBox::init();

my $global = EBox::Global->getInstance(1);
my $squid = $global->modInstance('squid');

try {
	$squid->restartService();
} catch EBox::Exceptions::Base with {
	print STDERR "Squid module failed to restart.\n";
};]]></programlisting>
		</example>

		<para>There are two functions that make it easy to perform two
		common tasks: getting an instance of every module and getting
		and instance of every module that implements some abstract
		class. These are <methodname>modInstances</methodname> and
		<methodname>modInstancesOfType</methodname>. Using them is straight
		forward:</para>

		<example>
			<title>Functions for instantiating more than one module</title>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[my $global = EBox::Global->getInstance(1);

# restart all modules
foreach my $mod (@{$global->modInstances()}) {
	$mod->restartService();
}

# restart only modules that implement the NetworkObserver class
foreach my $mod (@{$global->modInstancesOfType('EBox::NetworkObserver')}) {
	$mod->restartService();
}]]></programlisting>
		</example>

		<para>Restarting all the modules is even easier than
		that, <classname>EBox::Global</classname> provides the
		<methodname>restartAllModules</methodname> just for that. It's
		one of the methods that perform an operation on all the installed
		modules:</para>

		<variablelist>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><methodname>restartAllModules</methodname></term>
				<listitem>

					<para>Calls the <methodname>restartService</methodname> method
					on all the modules. This has the effect of restarting all the
					services handled by eBox. Config files are regenerated every time
					a service is restarted.</para>

				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><methodname>stopAllModules</methodname></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Calls the <methodname>stopService</methodname> method on
					all the modules, this includes the web based administration
					interface, so be careful.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><methodname>revokeAllModules</methodname></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Cancels the configuration changes that have been made
					in all the modules since the last time the configuration was
					saved.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><methodname>saveAllModules</methodname></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Saves the config changes in all modules.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

		</variablelist>

	</section>

	<section id="sect-exceptions">
		<title>Exceptions</title>

		<para>All error handling in eBox is implemented with
		java-style exceptions. These are provided by the perl
		module <classname>Error</classname>, you can check the perl
		documentation for that module for a detailed description on how
		to use exceptions in perl. eBox exceptions are defined in the
		<classname>EBox::Exceptions</classname> namespace.</para>

		<para>eBox provides a hierarchy of exceptions from which
		you can choose the most appropriate for each situation. All
		eBox exceptions inherit from one of these two exceptions:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para><classname>EBox::Exceptions::External</classname></para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para><classname>EBox::Exceptions::Internal</classname></para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>The difference between these two kinds is what the user will
		see when an uncaught exceptions occurs. The user interface framework
		will show the message contained in the exception unaltered if the
		exception is an external one. You should use external exceptions for
		user induced errors, like a syntax error in an IP address given by the
		user interface to the module backend.</para>

		<para>If the exception is internal it will log the error and assume
		something is wrong internally in eBox (a bug) or in the system in
		general. When an internal exception is caught by the GUI framework
		the user will see a generic error message, recommending him to check
		the system logs or seek technical support. Any exception, internal or
		external, may be used internally for other purposes, as long as it is
		caught before it goes all the way up to the GUI framework.</para>

		<para>If you can't find an exception for certain error condition,
		you have two options: create a new exception class, inheriting
		from either <classname>EBox::Exceptions::External</classname> or
		<classname>EBox::Exceptions::Internal</classname>, or just use one
		those two classes as generic exceptions:</para>

		<example>
			<title>Throwing a generic internal exception</title>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[if ($foo_condition) {
	throw EBox::Exceptions::Internal('Something happened!');
}]]></programlisting>
		</example>

		<para>As you can see, throwing exceptions follows a syntax very similar
		to Java's. Catching them is very similar too:</para>

		<example>
			<title>Catching an exception</title>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[use Error qw(:try);

sub foo
{
	my $bar = shift;

	try {
		$bar->doSomething();
	} catch EBox::Exceptions::Base with {
		# do nothing, just ignore the error
	};
}]]></programlisting>
		</example>

		<para>You can do whatever you like inside the <quote>catch</quote>
		clause. You may also write several <quote>catch</quote> clauses
		if you need to do different things for different exception types.
		<quote>otherwise</quote> and <quote>finally</quote> clauses are
		also allowed, for a detailed explanation about them just run
		<command>perldoc Error</command>. A very important detail is not to
		forget the semicolon after the last clause (the <quote>catch</quote>
		in the example), failing to do so may produce very weird results, this
		is due to the black magic that is used in the implementation of the
		try-catch idiom.</para>

	</section>

	<section id="sect-validate">
		<title>Data validation</title>

		<para>It is very important that every function exposed by each module
		validates its input data correctly. All of the arguments need to be
		checked, if this wasn't done a module could save syntactically wrong
		values in its configuration, and the underlying service would behave
		in an unpredictable way with the configuration file generated by the module.
		This also helps find bugs in the GUI front-end, and any other code that
		uses the module.</para>

		<para>The <classname>EBox::Validate</classname> perl module provides a
		bunch of functions to validate different types of data. All of this
		functions work the same way, their first argument is the value that's
		going to be checked. They return <literal>true</literal> if the value
		is correct, <literal>undef</literal> if it's not:</para>

		<example>
			<title>Using data validation functions</title>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[use EBox::Validate qw(:all);

my $ip = '192.168.0.1';

unless (checkIP($ip))
	print STDERR "$ip is invalid.\n";
}]]></programlisting>
		</example>

		<para>The usual thing to do if an argument is incorrect is to
		throw an exception. And most of the time the incorrect value will
		be an user-supplied one. For this reasons, all the functions in
		<classname>EBox::Validate</classname> provide an easy mechanism for
		throwing <classname>EBox::External</classname> exceptions. All you have
		to do is pass one more argument to them, with a name or description for
		the value you are trying to check. If you pass that argument and the
		validation fails, an exception will be thrown with a message indicating
		the name of the wrong field:</para>

		<example>
			<title>Using data validation functions with automatic error
			handling</title>

			<programlisting><![CDATA[checkIP($ip, 'IP address');
]]></programlisting>
		</example>

		<para>If you don't want an exception to be thrown, or if you want to
		throw a different kind of exception, just do not pass the last argument
		and handle the error yourself.</para>

	</section>

	<section id="sect-i18n">
		<title>i18n</title>

		<!-- FIXME - translate -->

		<para>eBox uses <application>gettext</application>, the GNU project's
		internationalization (i18n) platform. It makes it easy for translators
		to translate the eBox user interface into their own language.</para>

		<para>This section describes i18n from the point of view of both the
		developer (what steps must be taken to build a translatable module) and
		the translator (how to translate eBox into a new language).</para>

		<section id="sect-i18n-developers">
			<title>i18n developers</title>

			<para>Every eBox module has it's own gettext domain for the text
			strings it owns, the domain name is derived from the module
			name. Modules must set their gettext domain both in their
			constructor and in each one of their CGIs as explained in <xref
			linkend='sect-modconstructor'/> and <xref linkend='ex-cgi-domain'/>
			respectively.</para>

			<para>All files that contain translatable strings, including mason
			templates, must include the <classname>EBox::Gettext</classname>
			perl module. Also, every translatable string must be marked as such,
			using the <function>__</function> function as the following example
			shows:
			<programlisting>
print __("Hello world");
			</programlisting>
			This will enable the eBox build system to detect and extract all the
			translatable strings.</para>

			<para>If a string includes a variable you should not concatenate it:
			<programlisting>
print __("Edit ") . $group . __(" members"); # wrong
			</programlisting>
			This would make it impossible to correctly translate the whole
			sentence. The right way to do it is to use the
			<function>__x</function> function, which is a variant of
			<function>__</function> which lets you include variables:
			<programlisting>
print __x("Edit {group} members", group => $group); # right
			</programlisting>
			This way the translator can place the variable
			<varname>group</varname> in the right position in the sentence.</para>

			<para>If you want to mark a string as translable but determining not
			to translate it, you should use <methodname>__n</methodname> function. An
			example of usage is the following:</para>

			<example>
			  <title>Using <methodname>__n</methodname> function</title>
			  <programlisting>
my $options = [__n('Foo'), __n('Bar'), __n('Foobaz') ]; # As many as you want
print __($options[$index]);
			  </programlisting>
			</example>
			
			<para>The example showed above gives the chance to translator
			to translate only the option selected leaving the remainder
			(a high number normally) without a translation.</para>

			<para>If you follow this rules correctly, the build system will
			automatically generate PO files with all translatable strings
			included. These PO files can be easily translated, as explained in
			the next section.</para>

		</section>

		<section id="sect-i18n-translators">

			<title>i18n for translators</title>

			<para>Using GNU gettext as an i18n platform means we have the most
			widely used format for translations: PO files. Every eBox module
			has its one PO file for every available language. A translator just
			needs to translate all strings listed in that file in order to have a
			completely translated module. In case you are starting a translation
			for a new language from scratch, all you need to do is ask for a PO
			file to be generated for your language.</para>

			<para>A PO file contains the text strings in the original language
			(English) along with their translations. Each string may be in one
			for three possible states: translated (a translation exists for that
			string), fuzzy (a translation exists, but the original string has
			changed slightly) or untranslated: </para>

			<programlisting>
# translated string
msgid "Name"
msgstr "Nombre"

# fuzzy string
#, fuzzy
msgid "Interfaces"
msgstr "Interface"

# untranslated string
msgid "External"
msgstr ""
			</programlisting>

			<para>If the string includes the value of a variable when it is shown
			in the user interface you will see an entry like this one in the PO
			file:
			<programlisting>
msgid "Edit {group} members"
			</programlisting>
			In this case you just have to rewrite the sentence placing the name
			of the variable (in curly braces) in its proper place, but without
			translating it. The correct translation for this string in Spanish
			would look like this:
			<programlisting>
msgstr "Editar miembros de {group}"
			</programlisting>
			</para>

			<para>Even though it's possible to translate a PO file using any
			UTF-8 enabled text editor, it's a very good idea to use some
			of the tools created specifically for this task, like <ulink
			url='http://i18n.kde.org/tools/kbabel/'>KBabel</ulink> (*nix) or
			<ulink url='http://www.poedit.org/'>poEdit</ulink> (multi-platform).
			</para>

		</section>
  </section>

</chapter>
