<!-- vim: ts=2 sw=2
-->
<chapter id="ch-frontend">

	<title>Web frontend</title>

	<section id="sect-cgi">
		<title>CGIs</title>

		<para>The eBox administration interface is web-based,
		using <application>mod_perl</application> on top of
		<application>apache.</application> Information is fetched from the
		backends of the different modules by CGI scripts and it is displayed
		using the <application>mason</application> templating engine.</para>

		<!-- FIXME - screenshot -->

		<para> URLs are mapped from slash-separated paths to perl class names:
		the URL <uri>Network/Index</uri> is translated to the classname
		<classname>EBox::CGI::Network::Index</classname>. Actually, the root
		of the namespace is <uri>/ebox/</uri>, so the actual URL would be
		<uri>/ebox/Network/Index</uri>, but that part is handled automatically
		by the framework. So if you need to write a CGI to show some data
		or let the user configure something, just put your class in the
		<classname>EBox::CGI</classname> namespace and all matching requests
		will be passed on to it.</para>

		<para>There are lots of common functionality shared by most of
		the CGIs in eBox: error handling, input data validation, calling
		mason templates, showing messages and warnings, printing the menu,
		etc.</para>

		<para>For this reason there is a parent class from which all CGIs
		should be inherited. This class implements all those features
		with almost no intervention by its children, this is why many
		CGIs end up being around 20 lines long. All this functionality is
		actually split into two classes, because there is a small part
		of it that is specific to the client side of eBox. This part is
		kept in the client, and it is the class you should inherit from:
		<classname>EBox::CGI::ClientBase</classname>.</para>

		<!--+ FIXME - "the client side of ebox" and libebox are 
		    | not mentioned anywhere else.
				|
				| explanation should be in chapter 1
				+-->

		<para> The other class, <classname>EBox::CGI::Base</classname>, has
		most of the code, and it resides in <application>libebox</application>
		so that it can be reused by the server side.
		<classname>EBox::CGI::ClientBase</classname> inherits from
		<classname>EBox::CGI::Base</classname>, so you can safely forget there
		are two classes and just remember the former.</para>

		<para>Inheriting from <classname>EBox::CGI::ClientBase</classname> will
		give you a page with the usual title bar and menu, but an empty body. If
		you pass a <parameter>title</parameter> argument to the constructor of
		the parent class it will be shown too:</para>

		<example id='ex-cgi-hello'>
			<title>Hello world CGI</title>

			<programlisting><![CDATA[package EBox::CGI::Hello::World;

use strict;
use warnings;

use base 'EBox::CGI::ClientBase';

use EBox::Gettext;

sub new 
{
	my $class = shift;
	my $self = $class->SUPER::new('title' => __('Hello World!'), @_);
	bless($self, $class);
	return $self;
}]]></programlisting>
		</example>

		<para>In the vast majority of cases, you'll just need to implement
		the <methodname>_process</methodname> abstract method in your class
		to get the desired results. It is called by the parent class, which
		then performs different actions depending on the state of the object
		after the call to <methodname>_process</methodname>. There are certain
		attributes in the class you can set to change the parent's behavior.
		Your <methodname>_process</methodname> method will normally do one of
		these two things (maybe both):</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Obtain information from module backend and feed it to a mason
				template that will display it.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>Read input fields from the HTTP request and use them to
				perform some action on the module backend.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>The first thing there is to know is how to make a CGI use a
		mason template to display stuff. It's really easy, you can just pass a
		<parameter>template</parameter> argument to the parent's constructor,
		or set the <structfield>template</structfield> attribute at any time
		before your <methodname>_process</methodname> returns. This code shows
		both approaches:</para>

		<example>
			<title>Setting the mason template for a CGI</title>

			<programlisting><![CDATA[# Setting the template in the constructor
sub new 
{
	my $class = shift;
	my $self = $class->SUPER::new('title' => __('Hello World!'), 
					'template' => 'hello/world.mas',
					@_);
	bless($self, $class);
	return $self;
}

# Setting the template in _process
sub _process
{
	my $self = shift;
	$self->{template} = 'hello/world.mas';
}]]></programlisting>
		</example>

		<para>Secondly, we need to be able to pass some data to the mason
		template, this is done using the <structfield>params</structfield>
		attribute. It should be an array reference holding all parameters and
		their names. This is the <methodname>_process</methodname> method for
		the general configuration page (the one with the port, password and
		language):</para>

		<example>
			<title>Passing arguments to a mason template</title>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[sub _process
{
	my $self = shift;

	my $global = EBox::Global->getInstance();
	my $apache = $global->modInstance('apache');

	my @array = ();
	push(@array, 'port' => $apache->port());
	push(@array, 'lang' => EBox::locale());

	$self->{params} = \@array;
}]]></programlisting>
		</example>

		<para>That's all there is to using templates from the CGIs. The details
		about writing them are outlined in <xref linkend='sect-mason'/>.</para>

		<para> There is another mechanism to show data to the user. You can
		show messages and errors by setting the <structfield>msg</structfield>
		and <structfield>error</structfield> attributes to whatever text
		you want to display. Both types of messages are displayed in a
		box on the top of the page. You need to be a bit careful with
		the <structfield>error</structfield> attribute, since it will be
		overwritten if if an exception is caught by the parent class.</para>

		<!-- FIXME example -->

		<para>Reading arguments sent in the HTTP request is very straight
		forward. The parent class uses the <classname>CGI</classname> perl
		module to access that information, and provides a wrapper around its
		<function>param</function> function that does some checks on the input
		data. This is the <methodname>_process</methodname> method in the CGI that
		changes the web interface tcp port:</para>

		<example id='ex-http-params'>
			<title>Using parameters from the HTTP request</title>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[sub _process
{
	my $self = shift;

	my $global = EBox::Global->getInstance();
	my $apache = $global->modInstance('apache');

	$apache->setPort($self->param('port'));
}]]></programlisting>
		</example>

		<para>It is so simple because all checks on the data are performed
		by the backend (using the <classname>EBox::Validate</classname> perl
		module) and by the parent class. Another reason for the simplicity of the
		code above is that error handling is automatic.</para>

		<para>While you do all that stuff, exceptions may be thrown. Unless
		you have a good reason to catch an exception (i.e. you expect it and
		do not want it to be displayed as an error) you'll probably be just
		fine with the standard error handling, so you can simply forget the
		fact that exceptions could be thrown and write your code as if they
		did not exist. The standard behavior is that exceptions that inherit
		from <classname>EBox::Exceptions::Internal</classname> cause a generic
		error message, pointing the user to the logs if they need the details.
		<classname>EBox::Exceptions::External</classname> subclasses are
		displayed verbatim, the most typical use of these exceptions is when
		user-provided data is validated.</para>

		<para>The last bit you should learn is how to redirect requests to
		other CGIs. There are a few reasons why you could want to do that, e.g.
		you could write a CGI that takes some input parameters from the web
		browser, changes something in the module backend and then redirects
		the request to the CGI that displays the data. The CGI shown in <xref
		linkend='ex-http-params'/> does not call any mason template at all, it
		just changes the apache port and does nothing else. We want the user to
		see the same page they were seeing before changing the port, with the
		new value. <xref linkend='ex-http-redirect'/> shows the constructor for
		that CGI:</para>

		<example id='ex-http-redirect'>
			<title>Redirecting a request to a different CGI</title>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[sub new
	my $class = shift;
	my $self = $class->SUPER::new(@_);
	bless($self, $class);
	$self->{redirect} = "EBox/General";
	return $self;
}]]></programlisting>
		</example>

		<para>You can see that the constructor sets the
		<structfield>redirect</structfield> attribute to the URL of
		the page we want to redirect to. That's all there is to
		do, if <structfield>redirect</structfield> is set to some
		value, the parent class will do an HTTP redirect after the
		<methodname>_process</methodname> method returns.</para>

		<para>An HTTP redirect makes the browser issue a new HTTP request, so
		all the status data in the old request gets lost, but there are cases
		when you want to keep that data for the new CGI. This could be done
		passing GET parameters in the redirect URL, but it is simpler to do an
		internal redirect, without going through the browser.</para>

		<para> If you need to keep data, like a message or warning to the user,
		you can use the <structfield>chain</structfield> attribute. It works
		exactly the same way as <structfield>redirect</structfield> but instead
		of sending an HTTP response to the browser, the parent class parses the
		url, instantiates the matching CGI, copies all data into it and runs
		it. Messages and errors are copied automatically, the parameters in
		the HTTP request are not, since an error caused by one of them could
		propagate to the next CGI.</para>

		<!-- FIXME - example -->

		<para> If you need to keep HTTP parameters you can use the
		<methodname>keepParam</methodname> method in the parent class. It
		takes the name of the parameter as an argument and adds it to the
		list of parameters that will be copied to the new CGI if a "chain" is
		performed.</para>

		<!-- FIXME - example -->

		<para>Errors are a special case here. When an error happens you don't
		want redirects at all, as the error message would be lost. If an error
		happens and <structfield>redirect</structfield> has been set, then
		that value is used as if it was <structfield>chain</structfield>.
		However, sometimes you want to chain to a different CGI if there is
		an error, for example if the cause of the error is the absence of an
		input parameter necessary to show the page. If that's the case you
		can set the <structfield>errorchain</structfield> attribute, which
		will have a higher priority than <structfield>chain</structfield> and
		<structfield>redirect</structfield> if there's an error.</para>

		<para>Finally, the last detail there is to know about CGIs is how to
		make i18n work properly, both in the CGIs themselves and in mason
		templates. Since your module will not have the same gettext domain as
		the eBox framework, the framework needs to know your domain so that it
		can set it before calling your CGI and your template. It is as simple
		as setting the <structfield>domain</structfield> attribute in your
		object, the "Hello world" constructor in <xref linkend='ex-cgi-hello'/>
		would look like this:</para>

		<example id='ex-cgi-domain'>
			<title>Setting the gettext domain in a CGI</title>

			<programlisting><![CDATA[sub new 
{
	my $class = shift;
	my $self = $class->SUPER::new('title' => __('Hello World!'), @_);
	$self->{domain} = 'ebox-hello';
	bless($self, $class);
	return $self;
}]]></programlisting>
		</example>

		<para>
		If your title is translatable you should set it again in the
		<function>_process</function> function, like:
		<programlisting>
$self->{title} = __('Hello world');
		</programlisting>
		otherwise it will not be translated correctly.
		</para>

		<para>
		On the other hand, note that you should never use <function>__</function>
		with non translatable strings, like protocol names (i.e., DHCP, NTP, ...).
		</para>

	</section>

	<section id="sect-mason">
		<title>Mason templates</title>

		<para>This section will only cover a few basic aspects of writing
		mason templates, specially those details related to eBox. If you need
		complete documentation about a certain aspect you should check the
		<ulink url='http://www.masonhq.com/'>mason documentation</ulink> or the
		<ulink url='http://www.masonbook.com/'>mason book</ulink>. Additional
		examples can be found in <xref linkend='ch-examplemod'/>.</para>

		<para>The first thing your mason template will have is the declarations
		of the arguments it expects. Just write the name of the variables, one
		per line and you are done. Arguments declared as arrays in the template
		will be passed as array references by your CGI.</para> 

		<para> In our example we are going to give the template an array with
		names, and the template will say hello to each one of them separately.
		We use an empty array as a default value for the variable, although
		default values are optional. If none is given and you don't pass that
		argument to the template an exception will be thrown.</para>

		<example>
			<title>Declaring arguments in a mason template</title>

			<programlisting><![CDATA[<%args>
	@people => ()
</%args>]]></programlisting>
		</example>

		<para>The next thing is the initialization section, in this
		section we can write regular perl code. It is optional and most
		of the times not needed. However all eBox templates have one,
		because there is always the need to have i18n, so we import
		<classname>EBox::Gettext</classname>:</para>

		<example>
			<title>init section in mason templates</title>

			<programlisting><![CDATA[<%init>
use EBox::Gettext;
</%init>]]></programlisting>
		</example>

		<para>Now we can go on and write the body of the template. The idea is
		to just write HTML and use a couple of syntactic features to insert
		perl code wherever we need. First, we'll learn how to do control flow.
		All lines that start with a <literal>%</literal> are interpreted as
		perl code.</para>

		<example>
			<title>Embedding perl code in a mason template</title>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[<ul>
% foreach my $person (@people) {
	<li>Hello</li>
% }
</ul>]]></programlisting>
		</example>

		<para>We want to print the name of a person in each list item.
		Embedding perl expressions in the special tags <literal>&lt;%
		%&gt;</literal> prints the value of the expression in the output of
		the template. We are going to use this feature to print the name of
		the person and translate the "Hello" string (internationalization is
		explained in <xref linkend='sect-i18n'/>).</para>

		<example>
			<title>Printing strings in a mason template</title>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[<ul>
% foreach my $person (@people) {
	<li><% __('Hello') %> <% $person %></li>
% }
</ul>]]></programlisting>
		</example>

		<para>The ebox m4 macro exports the installation path for
		mason templates as <varname>TEMPLATESPATH</varname>, so you
		should install them under that directory, possibly creating a
		subdirectory for your module. Whenever you need to reference
		a template in your code, you can just use a path relative to
		<varname>TEMPLATESPATH</varname>. Following our example, will use a
		subdirectory named <filename>hello</filename> for our templates, and
		place a template called <filename>world.mas</filename> in it.</para>

		<section id='sect-gui-style'>
			<title>Standard GUI elements</title>

			<para>There are a few GUI elements that are displayed the same way
			in all eBox modules. Things like tips, messages, warnings, errors,
			tables and forms keep a common style. All this stuff is defined in
			the CSS file, so that all modules can show a consistent look and
			feel. Some of these elements have a dynamic behavior too, the tips
			are hidden when the page is loaded and shown if the user clicks on
			a link on the top-right corner of the page. This section gives an
			overview of all of these elements and how to use them to achieve an
			user interface that is consistent with all other eBox modules.</para>

			<para>All messages you want to display, which could be warnings about a
			risk if a certain action is performed, error notifications, help messages
			or other relevant information will be included in the mason templates
			using the same HTML code, but with different CSS styles.</para>

			<example>
				<title>HTML snippet for displaying messages</title>
				<programlisting><![CDATA[<div class='class-name'>
	Some message.
</div>]]></programlisting>
			</example>

			<variablelist>

				<title>CSS class names for informational messages</title>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><emphasis>help</emphasis></term>	

					<listitem>
						<para>For help information. Remember that information displayed
						using this style will be hidden unless the user decides to
						click on the help button.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><emphasis>note</emphasis></term>	

					<listitem>
						<para>Displays help or other useful information in a persistent
						way (it's not hidden like the <emphasis>help</emphasis> style).
						Use it when you want the user to be aware of some information
						without the need to click the help button.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><emphasis>warning</emphasis></term>	

					<listitem>
						<para>Displays a warning, e.g. if you want to make sure the
						user knows he is about to delete some data.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>

					<term><emphasis>error</emphasis></term>	

					<listitem>
						<para>For error notifications.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

			</variablelist>

			<para>You may want to display a list of data, e.g. a list
			of users. In this case you should use a table with elements
			<sgmltag>thead</sgmltag> and <sgmltag>tbody</sgmltag> to display the
			heading and the contents respectively. The CSS style for this kind of
			tables is <emphasis>dataTable</emphasis>.</para>

			<example id='ex-gui-table'>
				<title>A table to display data</title>
				<programlisting><![CDATA[<table class='dataTable'>
	<caption><% __('Object List') %></caption>
	<thead>
		<tr>
			<th class='tleft'><% __('Name') %></th>
			<th class='thOptions'><% __('Action') %></th>
		</tr>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
		<tr>
			<td></td>
			<td class='tcenter'>
				<a href='Del?objectname=<% $obj->{'name'} %>'>
						<img src='/data/images/delete.gif'
						     title="<% __('Delete') %>"
						     alt="<% __('Delete') %>"/>
				</a>
			</td>
		</tr>
	</tbody>
</table>]]></programlisting>
			</example>

			<para>As you can see in <xref linkend='ex-gui-table'/> the table has
			got a <sgmltag>caption</sgmltag> tag, which contains the title for
			the table. It is not required to include it, but it helps the user
			identify the kind of data we are listing.</para>

			<para>The rest of CSS styles are used to align text in the
			columns:</para>

			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><emphasis>tleft</emphasis></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>The heading columns (<sgmltag>thead</sgmltag>) are
						centered by default, we use <emphasis>tleft</emphasis> to force
						them to be left aligned to make it easier to read the data
						below.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><emphasis>tcenter</emphasis></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>The actions that the user can execute for each row in a
						listing are center-aligned using this style.</para>
					</listitem>

				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term><emphasis>thOptions</emphasis></term>

					<listitem>
						<para>It adjusts the column size to the minimum necessary and
						makes the contents center aligned.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>

			<para>Forms are displayed using a two-column table with the
			<emphasis>formTable</emphasis> style.</para>

			<example>
				<title>Data entry form</title>
				<programlisting><![CDATA[<table class='formTable'>
	<tr>
		<td class='tright'>
			<span class='ftitle'><% __('Name') %>:</span>	
		</td>
		<td>
			<input class='inputText' type='text' name='name' />
		</td>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td></td>
		<td>
			<input class='inputButton' type='submit' />
		</td>
	</tr>
</table>]]></programlisting>
			</example>

			<para>The first column contains the description for every field
			that the user is going to type in the form. The description column
			is right-aligned using the <emphasis>tright</emphasis> style, and
			text is written inside a <sgmltag>span</sgmltag> tag with the
			<emphasis>ftitle</emphasis> style.</para>

			<para>Text entries in the right column use the
			<emphasis>inputText</emphasis> class to decorate the input
			field.</para>

			<para>Form buttons use the <emphasis>inputButton</emphasis>
			style.</para>

		</section>

	</section>

	<section id="sect-menu">
		<title>The menu</title>

		<para>The menu in the administration interface is dynamically
		generated, letting all installed modules add new items
		and folders to it. There is a set of classes under
		the <classname>EBox::Menu</classname> namespace that
		can be used to build menu structures. The important
		ones are <classname>EBox::Menu::Item</classname> and
		<classname>EBox::Menu::Folder</classname>.</para>

		<para>The constructor for <classname>EBox::Menu::Item</classname>
		takes two named arguments, <parameter>text</parameter> and
		<parameter>url</parameter>. <parameter>url</parameter> should be
		relative to the root path for the configuration interface, for example
		the firewall packet filtering page has <uri>Firewall/Filter</uri> as
		its <parameter>url</parameter>.</para>

		<para>The <classname>EBox::Menu::Folder</classname> constructor does
		not take an <parameter>url</parameter> argument, but it takes a
		<parameter>name</parameter> one. The name is used internally as an
		identifier in the javascript menu implementation.</para>

		<para>Both items and folders have an optional
		<parameter>order</parameter> argument in their constructors, it should
		be an integer between 1 and 10, items in the menu are ordered from
		lower to higher values. The default is 5.</para>

		<para>A folder may contain items, so you can add
		<classname>EBox::Menu::Item</classname> instances to a
		<classname>EBox::Menu::Folder</classname>.</para>

		<para>Finally, the way to add menu items and/or folders to the menu is
		to implement the <methodname>menu</methodname> method in your module.
		This method gets a <classname>EBox::Menu::Root</classname> instance
		as an argument, and you can add as many items and folders to it as
		you want. This is the <methodname>menu</methodname> function for the
		firewall module:</para>

		<example>
			<title>Adding folders and items to the menu</title>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[sub menu
{
	my ($self, $root) = @_;
	my $folder = new EBox::Menu::Folder('name' => 'Firewall',
				'text' => __('Firewall'),
				'order' => 4);

	$folder->add(new EBox::Menu::Item('url' => 'Firewall/Filter',
				'text' => __('Packet Filter')));
	$folder->add(new EBox::Menu::Item('url' => 'Firewall/Redirects',
				'text' => __('Redirects')));

	$root->add($folder);
}]]></programlisting>
		</example>

		<!-- FIXME - screenshot -->

	</section>

	<section id="sect-summarypage">
		<title>Summary</title>

		<para>The eBox user interface has a "Summary" page where status
		information for every module is displayed. This page has two
		parts:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>The first part is a table with the status of all network
				services installed: whether they are running or not and buttons to
				restart them.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>The second part of the page has a separate section for each
				module, where more detailed information can be displayed.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<!-- FIXME  screenshot -->

		<para>Summary information is gathered by calling two abstract
		methods defined in <classname>EBox::Module</classname>, if you
		don't implement them then no information will be displayed about
		your module. <methodname>statusSummary</methodname> populates
		the table that will display the status of network services and
		<methodname>summary</methodname> creates the summary section for your
		module.</para>

		<para>The way the summary is built is quite similar to they way
		the menu is built, as shown in <xref linkend='sect-menu'/>. There
		are a bunch of classes in the <classname>EBox::Summary</classname>
		namespace that you can use to build your summary information,
		<methodname>statusSummary</methodname> should return an
		object of type <classname>EBox::Summary::Status</classname>
		while <methodname>summary</methodname> is free
		to return any object that is a subtype of
		<classname>EBox::Summary::Item</classname>, although most modules just
		return a <classname>EBox::Summary::Module</classname>.</para>

		<para> Each one of the <classname>EBox::Summary::Item</classname>
		subclasses has some attributes and can contain other
		<classname>EBox::Summary::Item</classname> objects, and they all print
		some HTML code. <classname>EBox::Summary::Module</classname> has a
		<structfield>title</structfield> attribute, when it is time to generate
		the page it prints the title and the html for its children below
		it.</para>

		<para>To see how the summary section is built, we are going to take
		a look at the network module. The output of its summary is a title
		and one section per network interface, with a bold title and a table
		that displays its MAC address, IP addresses, netmask, etc. <xref
		linkend='ex-network-summary'/> shows the important bits of its
		<methodname>summary</methodname> method.</para>

		<example id='ex-network-summary'>

			<title><methodname>summary</methodname> sample implementation</title>

			<programlisting><![CDATA[my $item = new EBox::Summary::Module(__("Network interfaces"));

foreach my $iface (@{$ifaces}) {
	my $status = __("down");
	my $section = new EBox::Summary::Section($iface);
	$item->add($section);

	if (iface_is_up($iface)) {
		$status = __("up");
	}
	$section->add(new EBox::Summary::Value (__("Status"), $status));

	my $ether = iface_mac_address($iface);
	if ($ether) {
		$section->add(new EBox::Summary::Value(
			__("MAC address"), $ether));
	}

	my @ips = iface_addresses($iface);
	foreach my $ip (@ips) {
		$section->add(new EBox::Summary::Value(
			__("IP address"), "$ip"));
	}
}
return $item;]]></programlisting>
		</example>

		<!-- FIXME screenshot -->

		<para>First an <classname>EBox::Summary::Module</classname> item is
		created, this object will hold all the summary information.</para>

		<para> Then an <classname>EBox::Summary::Section</classname>
		is created for each network interface, a section has a title
		(passed as an argument to its constructor) and it contains several
		<classname>EBox::Summary::Value</classname> objects, which display a
		name and an associated value as rows in a table within the section.
		So each several values are added to each section and the sections
		are added to the <classname>EBox::Summary::Module</classname>
		object. The result is a tree of objects, and its root is the
		<classname>EBox::Summary::Module</classname>, when it is asked to print
		itself it prints its title and asks each of its children to print
		itself. To see what it looks like just open the summary page in an eBox
		installation.</para>

		<!-- FIXME - screenshot -->

		<para><methodname>summary</methodname> may return any object as long as
		it inherits from <classname>EBox::Summary::Item</classname>, you can
		create your own if your needs are not covered by the standard items
		that come with the framework.</para>

		<para><methodname>statusSummary</methodname> is easier, it just has
		to return an <classname>EBox::Summary::Status</classname> object.
		The constructor for this class needs three arguments:</para>

		<itemizedlist>

			<listitem>
				<para>The name of the service.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>A boolean indicating whether the service is running.</para>
			</listitem>

			<listitem>
				<para>A boolean indicating whether the service is enabled or not.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para> The reason for this third argument is that services that the
		user should not be able to use the summary page to start services that
		have not been configured, so if, for example, the squid service is
		disabled, the user will have to go to the squid configuration page and
		enable the service there. <xref linkend='ex-squid-status'/> shows the
		<methodname>statusSummary</methodname> implementation in the squid
		module, along with some related methods.</para>

		<example id='ex-squid-status'>

			<title><methodname>statusSummary</methodname> sample
			implementation</title>

			<programlisting><![CDATA[sub statusSummary
{
	my $self = shift;
	return new EBox::Summary::Status('squid', __('HTTP Proxy'),
					$self->isRunning, $self->service);
}

sub isRunning
{
	my $self = shift;
	return $self->pidFileRunning(PIDFILE);
}

sub service
{
	my $self = shift;
	return $self->get_bool('active');
}]]></programlisting>

		</example>

		<para>Again, you can see what it looks like by checking out the Summary
		page in an eBox installation that has the squid module included.</para>

	</section>

</chapter>
