<chapter id="ch-mvc-internals">

  <title>Model-View-Controller internals</title>

  <simplesect id="mvc-internals-introduction">

    <title></title>

    <para>
      The main aim from this chapter is getting into the guts of the 
      <link linkend="sect-a-mvc-module">Model-View-Controller framework</link>. From an
      eBox developer is not required to get into if it is not strictly necessary.
      However, it could be useful to use it properly, to enhance it in some way or, 
      what is more, to add features not already addressed before.
    </para>

  </simplesect>

  <section id="internal-model-sect">
    <title>Model</title>

    <para>
      The main logic related to the data model is encapsulated on
      <classname>EBox::Model::DataTable</classname>. Its constructor requires at least
      a GConf module, i.e. an eBox module, a directory to store the data model and a Gettext
      domain which normally match with the GConf module one. The
      <link linkend="model-creation-sect">model description</link> is instanced
      just one using the Singleton method pattern at <methodname>table</methodname> method.
      As the <xref linkend="model-class-diagram-fig"/> depicts, there are 
      two main data model <classname>DataTable</classname> and 
      <classname>DataForm</classname> which represents the template system to be 
      used by real data models such as <classname>EnableForm</classname> or 
      <classname>ConfigureLogTable</classname>. 
    </para>

    <figure id="model-class-diagram-fig">
      <title>Data model class diagram</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/model-class-diagram.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      Data manipulation is done by
      <methodname>addRow</methodname>, <methodname>removeRow</methodname> and
      <methodname>setRow</methodname>, they are convenient methods to add, remove and
      update rows. The fields to fill the row are tailored to simplify and speed
      up the data input management from the HTTP request through a CGI. Moreover, a typed
      version is intended to be developed to ease the internal management and the exposed
      API as <xref linkend="model-access-sect"/> requires. For instance, to add
      a member in the <link linkend="member-model-definition">member table</link> you
      may use this piece of code:
    </para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[
$model->addRow( ( name => 'admin',
                  ipaddr_ip => '192.168.1.2',
                  ipaddr_mask => '32',
                  macaddr => '00:50:57:D0:11:08'
                )]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>
      The data from a model is stored and retrieved from GConf, some caching is done in
      order to speed up the data access times. In order to describe the GConf structure,
      it had better to use the result from <command>gconftool</command> command:
    </para>

    <example id="gconf-struct-model-example">
      <title>GConf structure from a model</title>
     
      <screen>
 data_version = 1
 /ebox/modules/objects/objectTable:
  /ebox/modules/objects/objectTable/keys:
   version = 44
   /ebox/modules/objects/objectTable/keys/x6666:
    readOnly = false
    name = RRHH
    /ebox/modules/objects/objectTable/keys/x6666/members:
     /ebox/modules/objects/objectTable/keys/x6666/members/keys:
      version = 1
      /ebox/modules/objects/objectTable/keys/x6666/members/keys/memb44:
       readOnly = false
       name = Claudia
       ipaddr_ip = 192.168.1.92
       ipaddr_mask = 32
   /ebox/modules/objects/objectTable/keys/x1850:
    readOnly = false
    name = MKT
    /ebox/modules/objects/objectTable/keys/x1850/members:
     /ebox/modules/objects/objectTable/keys/x1850/members/keys:
      version = 3
      /ebox/modules/objects/objectTable/keys/x1850/members/keys/memb9612:
       readOnly = false
       name = Florencia
       ipaddr_ip = 192.168.1.42
       ipaddr_mask = 32
      /ebox/modules/objects/objectTable/keys/x1850/members/keys/memb9390:
       readOnly = false
       name = Hugo
       ipaddr_ip = 192.168.1.46
       ipaddr_mask = 32
      /ebox/modules/objects/objectTable/keys/x1850/members/keys/memb2675:
       readOnly = false
       name = Silvina
       ipaddr_ip = 192.168.1.43
       ipaddr_mask = 32</screen>
    </example>

    <para>
      As you may see, the object data model stores two objects <emphasis>RRHH</emphasis>
      and <emphasis>MKT</emphasis> which the former saves one and the latter three members.
      The <varname>data_version</varname> indicates the data structure version in the same
      sense as <xref linkend="migration-scripts-sect"/> explains. Each data model stores 
      their values under <varname>keys/id</varname> directory, the id is obtained using
      <methodname>get_unique_id</methodname> as <xref linkend="sect-gconf"/> describes. 
      <property>Version</property> property is used by caching scheme, as you may notice is currently
      done per data model basis. As each object data model row has several members using
      the member data model, they are stored within the object directory as if another model.
      Each type has its value stored in GConf, for instance the field <parameter>name</parameter>
      for object <parameter>x6666</parameter> has as value <parameter>RHHH</parameter>.
      <property>readOnly</property> attribute indicates whether the row is read only or not.
    </para>

    <para>
      With regard to form data model, the GConf structure is quite simplified flattening
      the <parameter>keys/id</parameter> to the main GConf directory to let the form
      developer see its content easily.
    </para>

    <section id="model-relation-sect">
      <title>Model relationship</title>
      <para>
        Model relationship is describe through <classname>EBox::Types::HasMany</classname> and
        through <classname>EBox::Types::Select</classname> and whose management is done by 
        <classname>EBox::Model::ModelManager</classname> and 
        <classname>EBox::Model::DataTable</classname>. The former <emphasis>singleton</emphasis> 
        class coordinates all the available models along eBox, see
        <xref linkend="internal-publishing-sect"/> for details. Currently, there are two kind
        of relationships:
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>HasOne</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Determined by a select type which fetch its possible values or
              options from a foreign model, that is, from a value which is stored
              in a field in another model. To describe so, the
              <parameter>foreignModel</parameter> and <parameter>foreignField</parameter>
              must be set at table description. The model manager will store the 
              one-to-one relationship to maintain the referential integrity.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>HasMany</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>The HasMany relationship represents that a single field from 
              a data model stores another data model. The inner model looks like
              a submodel within the outer model and thus the <methodname>rows</methodname>
              and <methodname>printableValueRows</methodname> methods must return
              the information within that model per row. Likewise, when a row
              with a HasMany type is removed, the inner data model content is 
              deleted as well.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Furthermore, the <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Observer_pattern">Observer pattern</ulink>
        is applied to the data models as well. The models can subscribe to actions performed
        in foreign models such as addition, removal or updates. In order to achieve so, the
        table description must have <parameter>notifyActions</parameter> attribute as a hash
        reference indexing by the action description. So the model manager notifies an action
        is performed by a model calling <methodname>notifyForeignModelAction</methodname> method.
      </para>

      <para>
        Whenever an changing state action is performed, the data model asks to the model manager
        if any of other modules is using that row. If so and <parameter>automaticRemove</parameter> is
        set, a warning is shown before forcing the operation. If <parameter>automaticRemove</parameter>
        is not set, the data model must specify how it should act subscribing to the changing actions
        as it is described above.
      </para>

    </section>

    <section id="ebox-types-guts">
      <title>Developing eBox types</title>
      <para>
        The current eBox types selection is quite small and limited. We can see at first glance how
        its class structure at <xref linkend="types-class-diagram-fig"/>.
      </para>

      <figure id="types-class-diagram-fig">
	<title>eBox types class diagram</title>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/types-class-diagram.png"
		       format="PNG" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>
        As we can see <classname>Abstract</classname> manages the essential information for every
        eBox type. That is, their common attributes such as <parameter>optional</parameter>,
        <parameter>editable</parameter>, <parameter>printableValue</parameter>, etc. It also provides
        the main methods not to be overridden such as <methodname>setMemValue</methodname>, 
        <methodname>restoreFromHash</methodname> and so on. Basically, an eBox type allows the
        developer abstracting from Gconf storage and user input correctness since their handling
        is automatic. Furthermore, an eBox type is responsible for determining which setter
        and viewer must be used in eBox user interface by asking to <methodname>HTMLSetter</methodname>
        and <methodname>HTMLViewer</methodname> respectively.
      </para>

      <para>
        Firstly, in order to add a new eBox type is required to look over
        <xref linkend="types-class-diagram-fig"/> to check it if something similar has been
        developed before and just a class extension is required. Once we are sure a new
        type is needed for our models, these following methods, at least, must be overridden to
        make the type work:
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><methodname>_setMemValue</methodname></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Set the memory value for the type. It is assured that this
              method will be called if only there is something to fill the
              type and its content is valid.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><methodname>_storeInGConf</methodname></term>
            <listitem>
              <para> Store the given type in a GConf directory from a
              GConfModule. The expected behaviour is if it has no value to
              store, remove any previous stored data.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><methodname>_restoreFromHash</methodname></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Restore the type value from a hash reference which
              usually comes from <methodname>hash_from_dir</methodname>
              returned value.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><methodname>_paramIsValid</methodname></term>
            <listitem>
              <para> Check the correctness from the parameters passed. It assures
              that it is something to be checked</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><methodname>_paramIsSet</methodname></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Check if the given parameters contain the data needed to fill
              the type, i.e. it exists and it is not empty</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><methodname>_setDefaultValue</methodname></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Set the default value for the type</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        Apart from overriding these methods, it should set <parameter>HTMLSetter</parameter>,
        <parameter>HTMLViewer</parameter> and <parameter>type</parameter> on the constructor.
        The former two attributes determines which mason template, giving its path, must be
        used to set and show the type value respectively. The latter must be the class name
        in lower case. Methods <methodname>compareToHash</methodname>, <methodname>isEqualTo</methodname>
        and <methodname>printableValue</methodname> are recommended to be overridden.
      </para>

    </section>

  </section>

  <section id="internal-view-sect">
    <title>View</title>
    <para>
      Our Model-View-Controller framework uses in the View model Mason templates. Check out
      <xref linkend="sect-mason"/> for details about how to construct them. We use the
      <ulink url="http://www.masonhq.com/docs/manual/Devel.html#objectoriented_techniques">pseudo object
      oriented</ulink> that Mason provides. <xref linkend="view-class-diagram-fig"/> shows the templates
      which acts as viewers from the data model. The correspondence among model and view components is:
      <informaltable frame="none">
        <tgroup cols="2" align="center">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry><para>Model class</para></entry>
              <entry><para>View component</para></entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><para><classname>EBox::Model::DataTable</classname></para></entry>
              <entry><para><classname>tableBody.mas</classname></para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><para><classname>EBox::Model::DataForm</classname></para></entry>
              <entry><para><classname>form.mas</classname></para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </para>

      <figure id="view-class-diagram-fig">
	<title>View template system class diagram</title>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/view-class-diagram.png"
		       format="PNG" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>
        The methods implemented at <classname>modelViewer.mas</classname> component tries to
        abstract everything that a HTML table and a HTML form has in common. Every component,
        which subclasses from these components, must be called with the same arguments and
        call the parent <methodname>view</methodname> which is responsible to generate the HTML
        from the required parts. The main call must follow this pattern:

        <example id="main-component-example">
          <title>Component call main</title>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[
<%flags>
  inherit => '/ajax/modelViewer.mas'
</%flags>
<%args>
  $model
  $hasChanged
  $action => 'view'
</%args>
<%init>
  use EBox::Gettext;
  use EBox::Model::DataTable;
</%init>
<& PARENT:view,
   model => $model,
   hasChanged => $hasChanged,
   action     => $action,
&>]]>
          </programlisting>
        </example>
        <classname>modelViewer.mas</classname> has different elements to be overridden, a sub 
        component must implement <methodname>_body</methodname> "protected" method.
      </para>

      <para>
        The view interaction with the controller is done via JavaScript. Mason templates
        generates actions to be performed by the server, setting URL to be called using
        HTTP GET and POST methods. The JavaScript helper function calls are generated by
        the model itself through <methodname>changeRowJS</methodname>, 
        <methodname>addRowJS</methodname> and every method has "JS" as suffix.
      </para>

  </section>

  <section id="internal-controller-sect">
    <title>Controller</title>

    <para>
      The interaction among the data model and how it show and user interaction is applied
      to the data model is done by the controller. Controllers are a set of CGIs and
      some JavaScript helper functions which manage how the user interact with eBox data models.
    </para>

    <para>
      We have defined two kinds of CGIs, View and Controller. The former is a usual CGI
      which inherits from <classname>EBox::CGI::ClientBase</classname> and returns a complete
      HTML page to override the current one and contains the menu on the left and the top.
      Nevertheless, the latter is a new CGI class which inherits from
      <classname>EBox::CGI::ClientRawBase</classname> and gets back only the generated
      HTML page by the requested action as well as different HTTP code to be interpreted
      at the client side to set exceptions such as 500 or data in use 501. This is very useful
      to develop a simple and elegant way to manage exceptions within the application flow.
      The View CGI is called when the whole page loading is required, for instance clicking
      on a menu item and the Controller CGIs are called whenever an action (add, del, edit,
      move...) is done to a data model. This adaption is done allowing AJAX requests. This 
      MVC scheme now relies on <ulink url="http://prototypejs.org">Prototype JavaScript framework</ulink>
      to handle DOM and AJAX requests making eBox web application cross browser as far as 
      prototypeJS ensures it.
    </para>

    <para>
      Every JavaScript function is implemented in a separated file grouping by functionality.
      There is also some JavaScript classes to implement tabbing using JavaScript only. This increases
      its maintainability centralising the client side logic and it decouples from what is used
      to display the information, i.e. the mason templates.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section id="internal-publishing-sect">
    <title>Publishing models and CGI mapping</title>

    <para>
       Models and composite publishing is done by <classname>EBox::Model::ModelManager</classname>
       and <classname>EBox::Model::CompositeManager</classname> classes respectively. They 
       are <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Singleton_pattern">Singleton</ulink>
       classes, both follows the same logic. Once the instance is created, it sets up the
       models or composite by searching for implementation of the interfaces
       <classname>EBox::Model::ModelProvider</classname> and 
       <classname>EBox::Model::CompositeProvider</classname> among the eBox modules using
       <methodname>modInstancesOfType</methodname> from <classname>Global</classname> singleton
       class. Thus every instanced model and composite may be found in their managers.
    </para>

    <para>
      As you may notice, write a CGI for every model is not required anymore since there are
      general CGI to complete these tasks. Thus when a CGI is not found when the user
      asks for it by entering an URL, a look up inside the model and composite manager 
      is done. The URL to map must follow one these patterns:

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Model: <filename>/ebox/CGI/$moduleName/(View|Controller)/$modelName</filename></term>
          <listitem>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><varname>$moduleName</varname></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The module which the model belongs to, for instance,
                  <varname>Objects</varname> module</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>"View" or "Controller"</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Determine which kind of CGI must be called, both are explained in
                  <xref linkend="internal-controller-sect"/>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><varname>$modelName</varname></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The model name, this name must match with the
                  <property>tableName</property> attribute set at the table definition.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Composite: <filename>/ebox/CGI/$moduleName/Composite/$compositeName[/$actionName]</filename></term>
          <listitem>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><varname>$moduleName</varname></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The module which the composite belongs to, for instance,
                  <varname>Events</varname> module</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><varname>$compositeName</varname></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The composite name, its value must match with the 
                  <property>name</property> attribute set at the composite definition.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><varname>$actionName</varname></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>This optional part of the URL is used to determine if the CGI to call
                  is the View one, when no action name is provided, or the Controller one, when
                  the action name is determined, the action to perform is given to the 
                  controller at the creation time.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      Two examples from the previous patterns could be: <filename>/ebox/CGI/Objects/View/ObjectTable</filename> to
      show the objects stored in eBox and <filename>/ebox/CGI/Events/Composite/ConfigurationComposite/changeView</filename>
      to show the event configuration tables within a HTML divisor.

    </para>

    <para>
      Regarding to submodels, the CGI mapping is done by setting the directory on HTTP GET request
      as a parameter. By doing so, it is possible to know from where to get the data from. For instance,
      to view the members from the object whose identifier is <parameter>obje9972</parameter> the View 
      CGI URL must follow this pattern
      <filename>/ebox/CGI/Objects/View/MemberTable?directory=objectTable/keys/obje9972/members&amp;backview=/ebox/Object/View/MemberTable</filename>
      . The <parameter>backview</parameter> parameter is currently not implemented but its behaviour
      should follow the <emphasis>back</emphasis> action button from traditional web browsers.
    </para>

  </section>

</chapter>