<chapter id="ch-intro">

	<title>Introduction</title>

	<section id='sect-audience'>
		<title>Who is intended this guide for?</title>

		<para>This guide is intended for those people who
		already has eBox platform installed, or those who are
		evaluating its installation and want to know briefly
		its working and its possibilities.</para>
		
		<para>If your interest is focused on the internal
		working of this program or wants to learn how does the
		platform, which is written eBox with, please consult
		the "eBox Developers Guide".</para>

		<note>
			<para>This guide does not include general
			information about network services,
			communication protocols nor its
			application. These could be needed to fully
			understand the eBox, and its modules, way of
			working and utility.</para>
		</note>
	</section>

	<section id="sect-whatis">
		<title>What is eBox?</title>

		<para>eBox is a framework which has network services
		and a management application, for these services,
		through a web interface. Some of them are: firewall,
		file sharing, proxy-cache, content filter, mail
		server, NTP server, DHCP server, printer server,
		Jabber server and network objects management.</para>

		<para>eBox has a modular design, so it's possible
		its installation without all the available modules
		described on this guide. Anyway, you can check the
		information about the modules you don't own and
		inquire if they are useful for you, necessary or have
		an important real value for your current eBox
		platform.</para>
  </section>

	<section>
		<title>Terminology</title>

		<para><!--FIXME: ¿esta sección es como un glosario de términos de
eBox?--></para>
  </section>

	<section>
		<title>A first contact with the user interface</title>

		<para>Default URL to access to eBox administration
		interface is <ulink
		url="#">https://hostname/eBox</ulink>, where
		<emphasis>hostname</emphasis> is the IP address or the
		hostname where eBox is installed.</para>

		<para>User interface is divided on three main parts:</para>

		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Left vertical menu</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Left vertical menu, which is located at the left zone, has links to
					every service that can be configured with eBox. When any service has been
					selected in this menu, then a new submenu of the former service could
					appear. This submenu will let you configure and ask for the contents of each
					aspects of this service.
					</para>
					<!-- FIXME: left menu screenshot -->
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Horizontal upper menu</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Horizontal menu, located at the upper zone, has links to save the new
					changed made on contents part and make them real, to show the help and to
					log out from the application.</para>
					<!-- FIXME: top menu screenshot -->
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Main Content</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The content, which fits the central zone, has one or more forms with
					information about the service configuration, selected through the vertical
					left menu and/or its submenus. Sometimes, on the upper part of the content
					zone, will appear a tab bar, which will represent different subsections for
					the section we have accessed.</para>
					<!-- FIXME: content screenshot -->
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

		<note>
			<para>eBox items position could be modified anytime in future
			development.</para>
		</note>

		<para>An important detail of eBox is its way to do effective every
		change on the application. In other words, how and when changes will
		be saved.</para>

		<warning>
			<para>First, changes should be accepted on the
			current form, but it's needed to click on
			<guimenuitem>Save Changes</guimenuitem> (at
			the Horizontal upper menu) to make effective
			this changes and save them permanently. If you
			don't follow these simple steps, you will lose
			every single change you had made during the
			session.
			</para>
		</warning>

		<para>There are some exceptions when it's not necessary to "Save
		Changes". Just enough doing an action on the form where we are will
		make the work. These are the cases:

			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Users and groups management</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
							To add, modify or delete users
							or groups are immediate
							actions, and it's not
							necessary to "Save Changes" to
							make them effective.</para>
						</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>NTP Server</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>Date and time zone
							adjust for our system does not
							require changes save, either.
							</para>
						</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Language Changes</term>
						<listitem>
						<para>Interface language change is
						automatic and it's not needed to be
						saved permanently. It can be changed
						the eBox language on
						<menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu>
						<guimenuitem>General</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
						</para>
						</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Restart Services</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
						<!--FIXME:
							existirá después de la implantación del monitor de
servicios?-->
							</para>
						</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</para>
	</section>

</chapter>
