<chapter id="ch-users">

	<title>User management</title>

	<section id='sect-users-users'>
		<!-- Users -->
		<title>User accounts</title>

		<para>Through
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Users</guimenu>
		</menuchoice>
		is possible to create eBox users and modify their
		configuration.</para>

		<para>If you want to create a user, you just need to enter required
		information on the form, at the configuration window, and click
		<guibutton>Create</guibutton>. There are fields to enter user name,
                real name, user	comments, its password (with confirmation) and its
                user group which will belong to.</para>

		<para>After this, configuration for each created user can be modified,
                selecting the user from the selection list and click at
                <guibutton>Edit</guibutton>.</para> 

		<para>User edit window is dynamic, which means that its content can
		change depending on the eBox modules installed. There are two parts
		that will ever exist: on the upper zone, general user information will
		be shown to give the chance to modify it, including its comment, name
		and password (with confirmation); on the bottom you
		can see a 
                <guibutton>Delete</guibutton>
		button that you can click to remove the eBox user, and its
		dependencies with the installed modules. Between these parts, new
		information about each installed and enabled eBox modules can appear,
		including user-related options about: mail accounts, file sharing,
		printers sharing...</para>
	</section>

	<section id='sect-users-groups'>
		<!-- Groups -->
		<title>User groups</title>

		<para>Entering into
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Groups</guimenu>
		</menuchoice>
		you can create new groups or edit current groups configuration.</para>

		<para>To create a new group, you just need to enter a group name, a
		comment about the group (optional) and click "Create".</para>

		<para>If you want to edit a group, you have to follow the same
		procedure as with users. Just select it from the selection list at the
		bottom part and click <guibutton>Edit</guibutton>.</para>

		<para>Group edit window is dynamic as users edit window is. It
		includes the same two blocks: first one to edit comment group and
		choose which users belongs to the group, and the
		second one to <guibutton>Delete</guibutton> the
		selected group and
                all the dependencies
		with the installed modules. Between these two parts, group-related
		information of each eBox module installed, will be shown here.</para>
	</section>

</chapter>
