<chapter id="ch-files">

  <title>File sharing</title>

  <section id='sect-files'>
    <!-- File Sharing -->
    <title>File Sharing</title>
    
    <para>
      You can get into file sharing configuration entering into
      <menuchoice>
	<guimenu>File sharing</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>
      .
      To activate file sharing, just select from the status list, at the
      upper configuration page, "Enabled" status and accept the changes
      clicking at "Change".
    </para>

    <para>
      There are two working modes to this module. It
      can behave as a simple File Server using SMB/CIFS protocols or
      as well as a centralized authenticate method using Primary Domain
      Controller (PDC) to login on Windows NT-based.
    </para>

    <para>
      Both working modes needs the following fields configured:
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Domain name</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Only machines and users who belong to the same domain can
	      share their files between them. With this name eBox will
	      be recognize within the local network.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Netbios name</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Name applied to old NetBIOS framework which makes
	      eBox have a name within Windows environment.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Description</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      eBox description which goes with the Netbios name to
	      provide a detailed description within the network.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Quota limit</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Quota disk limit on MB to use for each
	    user. If you don't want to set any quota is OK
	    to fill this field with zero value.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id='sect-shared-files'>
    <title>User and group shared folders</title>

    <para>
      If file sharing module is installed and enabled in eBox,
      you may want to share files among users within the same group or
      publish files within the local network. To achieve so, you
      should go into
      <menuchoice>
	<guimenu>Users</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>
      and edit the user which can publish files on the local
      network. There, you can enable this user to do so and ,
      furthermore, you can set him administrative rights to add
      machines to the domain, if the working mode is
      <emphasis>PDC</emphasis>. Check <link
      linkend='sect-users-users'>User accounts</link> to know more
      about the eBox user configuration.
    </para>

    <para>
      If you want to share a directory among the users within a group,
      you should reach
      <menuchoice>
	<guimenu>Groups</guimenu>
      </menuchoice>
      and edit the group you want. There you can set a name to that
      directory.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>
	The current file permission allows to read, write and
	execute a file to the owner and read and write to the
	group. Regarding to subdirectories, the setgid bit is set, so
	subdirectories group owner will be the group. Furthermore, the
	new subdirectories will have full access to the group.
      </para>
      
    </note>

  </section>

</chapter>
