<chapter id="ch-printers">

	<title>Printers</title>

	<section id='sect-printers-new'>
		<!-- eBox->Add printer -->
		<title>Add new printers</title>

		<para>You can add new printers on eBox at
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Printers</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Add printer</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
		. Each new printer could  be shared on your network,
		allowing or not users and groups accesses.
		</para>

		<para>Adding a new printer requires to know some information like how
		it's connected with eBox, manufacturer, model and driver if you want
		to get a full-working system. eBox will ask the information and will
		offer existing possibilities to configure the new printer.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id='sect-printers-admin'>
		<!-- eBox->Printers admin -->
		<title>Printers administration</title>

		<para>Going into
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Printers</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Printers admin</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
		you can access into eBox printer administration.
		</para>

	        <para>We can review and modify the printer sharing current status in
		the system, and see the printer list configured on the system. We also
		can remove them from eBox or modify its status and its current
		parameters.</para>

		<para>Any moment after the addition of a new printer, you can remove
		it clicking at its own corresponding action, or access to its specific
		configuration clicking at "Edit" on that printer.
		</para>

		<para>If you decide to edit the printer configuration, a four-tabbed
		windows will appear, which give access to each configuration item on
		the printer management:
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Printer details</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>You can review and modify every details
					related to manufacturer, model and driver
					about selected printer.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Driver options</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Configuration options depends on the
					installed driver. eBox will show, frequently,
					a list with the possible values for each
					option, making easier the configuration, and
					avoiding incorrect values of configured parameters.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Configuration options</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>This part allows to modify the printer
					connection method with eBox. Depending on if
					it's USB, parallel port or samba,
					configuration options will be different.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Pending jobs</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Pending jobs of the selected printer are
					shown. For each job is shown its ID, owner,
					name, size and creation date. A job can be
					also cancelled using its action button,
					removing it from the job list.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		</para>
	</section>

</chapter>
