<chapter id="ch-mail">

	<title>Mail server</title>

	<section id='sect-mail-config'>
		<!-- Mail->General->Settings -->
		<title>General Settings</title>

		<para>To enter at the General settings on the eBox
		mail server, go to
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Mail</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>General</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		. At the configuration page, upper zone, some tabs
		will be shown to configure different things on the
		mail server:
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Services</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Choosing services tab, we can enable or
					disable mail server, ask for authentication
					to mail users or allow free access, and use
					(or not) TLS to cipher communications between
					server and client. Also, you can enable POP3
					and IMAP requiring users to use SSL, just
					allowing them the decision or deny SSL use.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Configuration</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The configuration shown below this tab,
					allow to set a relay server, simply using its
					IP address. It also allows to set a maximum
					message limit, accepted by the server, and a
					default size limit for the new mail
					accounts. At the bottom, you can set the relay
					policy for each network object, which have a
					higher priority over the general configuration
					option at Services tab.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>External filter</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>From this tab, you can enable an
					external filter to control eBox mail
					messages. To enable it, we need to set a port
					on eBox system to establish communications,
					and know IP address and port where the filter
					is located.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id='sect-mail-vdomain'>
		<!-- Mail->Virtual domains-->
		<title>Domain management</title>

		<para>
		At
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Mail</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Virtual domains</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
	        you can manage virtual domains, which give a name
	        domain to the mail accounts of the different eBox
	        users.</para>

		<para>To create a new domain, you just need to choose a name for the
		domain and a default size for the eBox users' mailboxes who belong to
		the domain. Later, you can modify the default mailbox size and force
		changes at existing mailboxes to any size, from the menu you can find
		clicking at <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> for the desired domain. If you want to remove one
		existing domain, just click at the <guibutton>Remove</guibutton> button for that domain.</para>
	</section>

	<section id='sect-mail-accounts'>
		<title>Accounts and mail aliases</title>

		<para>If mail module is installed and enabled in eBox,
		and you wish to create one mail account to a user, it
		must be done going into
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Users</guimenu>
		</menuchoice>
		and editing our desired user, where you can also set
		an alias for the user mail address. Check <link
		linkend='sect-users-users'>User accounts</link> to
		know more about the eBox user configuration.</para>

		<para>To set an alias to user groups, you have to get
		the group configuration page using 
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Groups</guimenu>
		</menuchoice>
		. If mail module is enabled, an alias can be set for
	        all group members. Check <link
	        linkend='sect-users-groups'>User groups</link> to know
	        how to get to group configuration.
		</para>
	</section>

</chapter>
