<chapter id="ch-dhcp">

	<title>DHCP Server</title>
	
	<section>
		<title>DHCP Server</title>
	
		<para>You can enter into DHCP Server configuration
		going into
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>DHCP</guimenu>
			</menuchoice>
		.
		</para>

		<para>You just will be able to configure DHCP server if there is any
		network interface declared as Static. If there are different
		interfaces set as static, you could choose which one will be
		configured through the upper tabs, just below the status select
		list.</para>
      
		<para>If you want to enable DHCP server, select from the selection
		list (at the upper zone of the configuration page), status "Enabled"
		and accept the form clicking at "Change".</para>
			
		<para>Working configuration about DHCP server can be adjusted with
		these options:
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Options</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>These options are not required, and
					leave them blank is OK. They are used to
					define the default gateway, name domain search
					and primary and secondary Name Servers 
					in the network.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Ranges</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Range lists can be created with some
					values you could like to assign to network
					hosts. This lists must not have matches
					between them and every allocatable addresses
					must belong to the available range shown above
					the ranges list. If no list is created, every
					range will be used to assign addresses to the
					network.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Static assignments</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>A fixed IP can be assigned (if belongs
					to the available range) to a MAC address from
					the network. You just need to create an
					item at the static assignation list which has
					the MAC address and the required IP address.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		</para>
		</section>
</chapter>
