<chapter id="ch-dhcp">

  <title>DHCP Server</title>
	
  <section id="dhcp-serv-sect">
    <title>DHCP Server</title>
	
    <para>You can enter into DHCP Server configuration
    going into
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>DHCP</guimenu>
    </menuchoice>
    .
    </para>

    <para>You just will be able to configure DHCP server if there is any
    network interface declared as Static. If there are different
    interfaces set as static, you could choose which one will be
    configured through the selection element. DHCP server works as
    well with virtual static interfaces. In order to serve IP
    addresses in a static interface is required to set at least a range
    or a fixed address mapping.</para>
      
    <para>If you want to enable DHCP server, check out <xref
    linkend="sect-mod-status"/> for details to do so.</para>
			
    <para>Working configuration about DHCP server can be adjusted with
    these options:
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Options</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>There are two tabs to set the options for the DHCP
          server in that interface.
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term><guilabel>Common options</guilabel></term>
              <listitem>
              <para>These options set:
              <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                  <term>Default gateway</term>
                  <listitem><para>Indicate DHCP clients which is the
                  next step to go if they don't know how to reach the
                  destination. Their values may be eBox itself, a
                  custom IP address in CIDR format, none or a
                  configured gateway done in <xref
                  linkend="sect-gateways"/>.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                  <term>Search domain</term>
                  <listitem><para>Indicate DHCP clients which is the
                  search domain to add when a not fully qualified
                  domain is given to the DNS. Its value may be a
                  custom one, none or one of the configured in the
                  <link linkend="ch-dns">DNS module</link>.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                  <term>Primary nameserver</term>
                  <listitem><para>Indicate DHCP clients which is the
                  primary name server to ask for domain name - IP
                  address queries. Its value may be the eBox itself, a
                  custom one using its IP address or none.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                  <term>Secondary nameserver</term>
                  <listitem><para>Indicate DHCP clients which is the
                  secondary name server to ask for domain name - IP
                  address queries when the primary one is down. Its
                  value is optional and it must a valid host IP
                  address.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
              </variablelist>
              </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                  <term><guilabel>Advanced options</guilabel></term>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>These set of options are managed only
                    advanced users to determine a leased time and thin
                    client options.
                    <variablelist>
                      <varlistentry>
                        <term>Lease times</term>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>The leased time is those which a given
                          IP address is set as valid by the DHCP
                          server. You may modify the default values to
                          set a new default one and a maximum one as
                          well.</para>
                        </listitem>
                      </varlistentry>
                      <varlistentry>
                        <term>Thin client</term>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>These options allows to use eBox as a
                          thin client (proxy) server. It acts as proxy
                          thin client server when the next server
                          option points to another computer. If it set
                          as thin client server by setting the option
                          as <emphasis>eBox</emphasis>, then you may
                          include all files to load in thin client
                          such as boot files and parameters in a fixed
                          directory as help outputs.</para>
                        </listitem>
                      </varlistentry>
                    </variablelist>
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Ranges</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Range lists can be created with some values you would
          like to assign to network hosts. These lists must not have matches
          between them and every allocatable addresses must belong to
          the available range shown above the ranges list.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Static assignments</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A fixed IP can be assigned (if belongs to the
          available range) to a MAC address from the network. You just
          need to create an item at the static assignation list which has
          the MAC address and the required IP address.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    Take into account that every setting in ranges list and fixed
    address mappings must not overlap each other. Not only in the same
    interface but also in the remainder ones. These checks are done
    automatically by eBox.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
