<chapter id="ch-dns">

		<!-- DNS Cache -->
		<title>DNS service</title>

		<para>
		The DNS service can work just as as a DNS cache server, or
		as a proper DNS server to answer queries for your local
		domains
		</para>

		<section id='sect-dns-cache'>
		<title>DNS cache</title>
		 <para>
		 When  the DNS service is enabled it will automatically work as
		 a DNS cache service, that is, several DNS requests will be
		 resolved as an only external DNS request, reducing response
		 time and network traffic with most visited hosts.
		 </para>
		</section>

		<section id='sect-dns-server'>
		<title>DNS server</title>
		 <para>
		 There is a more advanced feature that will allow you to create
		 domains for your local network. This is very useful if you want
		 your users to use host names for your local machines instead of
		 recalling IPs.
		 </para>

		 <para>
		 The DNS service in eBox features a simple to use server which
		 allows you to add domains. And within each domain, you can add
		 machines and aliases for each one of them. Note that it lacks
		 features such as setting MX register, zone transfer and so
		 forth. Those features will be added in the future.
		 </para>
	         
		 <variablelist>
	          <varlistentry>
	 	   <term>Domains</term>
		    <listitem>
		     <para>
		      You can add as many domains as you need. Remember that
		      your hosts will be added taking a domain as a root.
		     </para>
		     <para>
		     To add a domain, go to 
		     <menuchoice><guimenu>DNS</guimenu></menuchoice>, 
                     and just type a domain's name in the table placed below 
		     the service configuration. As we mentioned you can 
		     add as many domains as you need.
		     </para>
		    </listitem>
	           </varlistentry>

		   <varlistentry>
		    <term>Hosts</term>
		    <listitem>
		     <para>
		      The next step, after creating a domain, is adding 
		      host names to the domain. What you are doing here 
		      is binding an IP address to a host name. 
		     </para>

		     <para>
		      To add a host name, you must edit the domain you would
		      like to add the host to. To do so, click on the pencil
		      icon in the domain table. A new screen will show up. In
		      this new screen you will be able to add a host name and
		      its corresponding IP.
		     </para>

		     <para>
		      In case of having an IP address with more than one name associated to it, you can add <emphasis>aliases</emphasis> right below the first host name added.
		     </para>
		    </listitem>
		   </varlistentry>

		 </variablelist>

		</section>

</chapter>
