<chapter id="ch-jabber">

	<title>Jabber Server</title>
	
	<section id="jabber-serv-sect">
		<title>Jabber Server</title>
	
		<para>You can get to Jabber server configuration at
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Jabber</guimenu>
			</menuchoice>
		and with each user options.</para>

		<para>Jabber server configures a instant messenger network access, for
		a local network or with external connection. It also handles
		authentication per-user, allowing or not its access to each one.</para>
		
		<para>If you want to enable Jabber server, check out
                <xref linkend="sect-mod-status"/> for details to do so.
                </para>

		<para>You can configure Jabber server behavior by setting these options:
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Domain Name</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>Every account on a Jabber server has this syntax:
						user@domain. Users shall use this syntax on their IM clients to
						chat. For this reason, the domain name should be resolved by the
						user's PC, and resolved by the rest of Internet if external access
						is configured.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Global Jabber network connection</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>Jabber server can be part of the planet-wide Jabber network;
						or work as a stand-alone server on a corporative network. This
						option allows to select its behavior.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>SSL Support</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>Authentication and data transmission between Jabber user and
						the server can be made of three different ways:
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem>
									<para>First, selecting "No" value will make
									a plain communication between both
									parts.</para>
								</listitem>
								<listitem>
									<para>Second option, "Optional". It allows
									the user to choose if communication with the
									server should be encrypted, with SSL, or
									plain.</para> 
								</listitem>
								<listitem>
									<para>Last, if SSL access is "Required", IM
									client must allow SSL authentication to get
									connected to Jabber server.</para>
								</listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</para>

		<para>On each user configuration, we can find two new options for its Jabber access configuration:
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>User account</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>It can be checked or not, which will allow the user access to
						the Jabber server.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>User has administration rights</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>A user with administration privileges can be notified with
						some server events, or make some actions only available to admin
						users. Please, check Jabber documentation if you need to know about
						the full set of privileges of a Jabber network administrator.</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</para>
		</section>
	
</chapter>
