<!-- vim: ts=2 sw=2 tw=75
-->
<chapter id='ch-source'>

	<title>Installing eBox from source</title>
	<tip>
	<para>Before installing eBox from source you should be aware that the
	preferred installation method are the provided Debian packages, which
	have a much easier installation process.</para>
	</tip>

	<para>eBox is composed of a framework and modules using it. Before
	installing any module you need to install the packages providing the
	framework, namely libebox and ebox.</para>

	<para>Once you have installed those packages you should be able to
	install new modules. Anyway you should take into account that some
	modules may depend on another ones and you should install them in the
	right order </para>

	<para>The new modules will be able to detect the paths used by the
	framework and will install themselves in the right place. </para>

	<section id='getting-source'>

		<title>Getting the sources</title>

		<para>
		The first thing needed to install eBox from sources is obviously the
		source itself. You can get it from <ulink
		url="http://projects.warp.es/ebox/"/>.
		</para>

		<para>You should get at least the core packages (libebox and ebox),
		the basic modules (objects, network and firewall) and then your desired
		module selection.</para>

		<para>
		Once we have the gzipped tar files of the latest eBox version we should
		be able to start installing them. To extract the contents of a tarball
		you just need to run:
		<screen>	
		tar zxvf ebox-&lt;module&gt;-&lt;version&gt;.tar.gz
		</screen>
		</para>

	</section>

	<section id='installing-source'>

		<title>Installing from source</title>

		<note>
		<para>
		During the next sections will appear some commands that you should run,
		the ones preceded by $ should be run as a normal user and the ones
		preceded by # must be run as root.
		</para>
		</note>

		<section id='installing-basic-ebox'>

			<title>Installing a basic eBox: firewall and proxy</title>

			<para>Now we will proceed to install a basic eBox with firewall and
			proxy capabilities. To achieve this we should install the firewall and
			squid modules and every other module required by them. To get a list of
			dependencies for a given module you can check the INSTALL file provided
			in the tarball.</para>

			<section id='installing-libebox'>
				<title>Installing libebox</title>
				<para>libebox contains some code shared by eBox client and eBox server
				and should always be the first package installed. Before installing it
				we should install every dependency that appears in the INSTALL file. We
				can install the packages easily using apt-get:
				<screen>
				# apt-get install perl perl-modules sudo
				# apt-get install liblog-dispatch-perl liblog-log4perl-perl
				# apt-get install liblocale-gettext-perl libnet-ip-perl liberror-perl
				# apt-get install libdevel-stacktrace-perl libhtml-mason-perl gettext
				</screen>
				</para>

				<para>The next step is to run the script configure to have it detect
				if everything is correctly installed and where should it install eBox.
				configure accepts several arguments to change its behaviour, for
				example, we will provide the localstatedir parameter to install
				variable data in a non-default directory:
				<screen>
				$ ./configure --localstatedir=/var/
				</screen>
				</para>

				<para>
				Once we have run configure we are ready to install libebox by running
				as root:
				<screen>
				# make install
				</screen>
				</para>
				<para>
				You can check if everything is working correctly by trying to run
				this command:
				<screen>
				$ perl -MEBox -e 'print EBox::Config->version'
				</screen>
				If it prints the eBox version then you're in the right way.
				</para>
			</section>

			<section id='installing-ebox-base'>

				<title>Installing eBox base</title>

				<para>eBox base (or just ebox) is the module that contains the
				framework to build eBox modules upon it and the one with the longer
				installation process. As usual we will check the INSTALL file for
				required software and will install it using apt-get:
				<screen>
				# apt-get install apache-perl libapache-mod-perl libapache-mod-ssl
				# apt-get install libapache-authcookie-perl libapache-singleton-perl
				# apt-get install libsys-cpu-perl libsys-cpuload-perl
				# apt-get install libgnome2-gconf-perl libproc-process-perl
				</screen>
				</para>

				<para>
				Once we have installed every requisite we can proceed to run the
				<command>configure</command> script, it will autodetect Apache and
				libebox, and then running <command>make install</command> will put
				everything in the right place:
				<screen>
				$ ./configure
				# make install
				</screen>
				</para>

				<para>From now on we will consider <filename>/var/lib/ebox</filename>
				the home directory of ebox, if you haven't used --localstatedir=/var
				in libebox configure, you should replace every
				<filename>/var/lib/ebox</filename> appearance with the output of:
				<screen>
				$ echo $(perl -MEBox -e 'print EBox::Config->var')/lib/ebox
				</screen>
				</para>

				<para>
				eBox needs unprivileged user and group in your system to run safely, so we
				will create the ebox user and group now. The home for the user will be
				/var/lib/ebox:
				<screen>
				# addgroup --system ebox
				# adduser --system --home /var/lib/ebox/ --no-create-home \
					 --disabled-password --ingroup ebox ebox 
				</screen>
				</para>	

				<para>eBox needs several directories inside its home to work properly,
				we will create a <filename>log</filename> directory to hold the eBox
				logs, a <filename>tmp</filename> to store temporary files and a
				<filename>gconf</filename> directory to store gconf data:
				<screen>
				# mkdir /var/lib/ebox/tmp
				# mkdir /var/lib/ebox/log
				# mkdir /var/lib/ebox/gconf
				</screen>
				</para>

				<para>gconf needs a <filename>.gconf.path</filename> file to know where
				should it store preferences for the ebox users. You must copy this file
				from the <filename>conf</filename> directory in the ebox sources:
				<screen>
				# cp conf/.gconf.path /var/lib/ebox
				</screen>
				</para>
				
				<para>
				Now we should change the owner of the /var/lib/ebox directory to the
				ebox user, including every subdirectory:
				<screen>
				# chown -R ebox.ebox /var/lib/ebox/
				</screen>
				</para>

				<para>
				eBox uses sudo to grant the ebox user the rights to run some commands under
				a privileged account, every module includes the commands that it needs
				to run as root. The <command>ebox-sudoers</command> can gather that
				commands from the currently installed modules and generate a correct
				sudoers file. Basically, every time you install a new eBox module you
				need to update it like this:
				<screen>
				# ebox-sudoers > /etc/sudoers
				</screen>
				Note that this will overwrite your <filename>/etc/sudoers</filename>
				file, so make a backup if you want to keep it safe.
				</para>

				<para>
				Usually eBox takes control of every service it provides, including
				starting and stopping it, so the general rule is that you need to
				remove the links from /etc/rc2.d to avoid the services being started on
				system launch. The eBox base module manages apache-perl, so we will
				remove the links from the rc.d directories. The safer way to do this
				is:
				<screen>
				# update-rc.d -f apache-perl remove
				</screen>
				as it will work for both sysv-rc and file-rc init systems.
				</para>

				<para>
				Now we should make sure that ebox is run on startup, a ebox init
				script is provided in the tools directory in the sources, we just need
				to copy it to <filename>/etc/init.d</filename> and run update-rc.d:
				<screen>
				# cp tools/ebox /etc/init.d
				# update-rc.d ebox defaults 99
				</screen>
				</para>

				<para>
				To start eBox immediately you can now run:
				<screen>
				# /etc/init.d/ebox start
				</screen>
				Once eBox is launched you should be able to access the administration
				interface at https://&lt;ip address&gt;/, it should like this:
				<figure><title>eBox login page</title>
				<graphic fileref="images/ebox.png"/>
				</figure>
				</para>

				<para>The default password is 'ebox'. It may be changed in the general
				configuration page. If everything works correctly you should see
				the eBox summary page:
				<figure><title>eBox summary page</title>
				<graphic fileref="images/ebox-base.png"/>
				</figure>
				As you will notice eBox is quite useless without installed modules so
				we will quickly move to the next section to install more modules that
				provide it nice features.
				</para>

			</section>

			<section id='installing-basic-modules'>
				<title>Installing eBox basic modules: network, objects and firewall</title>
				<para>
				There are three modules that are required by almost every other eBox
				module, they are objects, network and firewall.
				</para>

				<para>
				As usual, the first step is to install the required Debian packages:
				<screen>
				# apt-get install dhcp3-client iproute vlan     # network module
				# apt-get install iptables                      # firewall module
				</screen>
				You should note that there are also requirements for the Linux kernel
				installed in the machine, it should have VLAN (for network module) and
				Netfilter (for firewall module) support (either built-in or with modules).
				</para>

				<para>
				Once the prerequisites have been installed you just need to run
				<screen>
				$ ./configure
				# make install
				</screen>
				for each module. The firewall module should be the last as it depends
				on both objects and network module. The network module can import the
				current network configuration stored in
				<filename>/etc/network/interfaces</filename> and
				<filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename>. To do it you just need to run
				the <command>ebox-netcfg-import</command> command.
				</para>

				<para>
				Just to be sure that eBox gets the correct list of modules from gconf,
				you should kill every running gconfd instance:
				<screen>
				# pkill gconf
				</screen>
				After this you can safely run ebox-sudoers to overwrite the old
				sudoers file:
				<screen>
				# ebox-sudoers > /etc/sudoers
				</screen>
				</para>

				<para>If you point your browser to the eBox administrative
				interface again the new modules should appear there:
				<figure><title>eBox with the basic modules installed</title>
				<graphic fileref="images/ebox-basic-modules.png"/>
				</figure>
				</para>

			</section>

			<section id='installing-proxy'>

				<title>Installing the HTTP proxy module</title>

				<para>
				Now we will finish our installation adding the Squid module, which
				provides a HTTP proxy with optional content filter.  We will follow
				the usual procedure after reading the INSTALL file:
				<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>
				Install the required packages:
				<screen>
				# apt-get install squid dansguardian
				</screen>
				</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para>
				Run configure and make install:
				<screen>
				$ ./configure
				# make install
				</screen>
				</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para>
				Don't start the associated services on system launch:
				<screen>
				# update-rc.d -f squid remove
				# update-rc.d -f dansguardian remove
				</screen>
				</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para>
				Update the <filename>sudoers</filename> file:
				<screen>
				# pkill gconf
				# ebox-sudoers > /etc/sudoers
				</screen>
				</para></listitem>

				</itemizedlist>
				</para>

				<para>
				After performing the previous steps, we can check if everything went ok
				in the eBox administrative interface, where a Squid menu entry should
				have appeared.
				</para>

			</section>
		</section>
		
		<section id='installing-LDAP-modules'>	
			<title>Installing LDAP modules</title>
			<para>
			There are several eBox modules that use the concept of users and
			groups, for example, the Samba module, which allows you to setup
			file sharing or the mail module that provides mail accounts for users.
			</para>

			<para>
			The module that manages users in eBox is called usersandgroups and
			stores them in an LDAP directory. You should install this module before
			any other one that requires the existance of users. As usual, this
			requirement will be clearly stated in the INSTALL file.
			</para>

			<para>
			Although the installation steps are basically the same as the used to
			install the previous modules, there are some tricky steps in the process.
			In the next section we will install the usersandgroups and Samba
			modules.
			</para>

			<section id='installing-usersandgroups'>
				<title>Installing the usersandgroups module</title>
				<para>
				First of all you should perform the standard installation procedure:
				<screen>
				# apt-get install slapd libnet-ldap-perl
				$ ./configure
				# make install
				# pkill gconf
				# ebox-sudoers > /etc/sudoers
				</screen>
				</para>
				<para>
				FIXME magnetic (AFAIK the INSTALL file is not up-to-date)
				</para>
			</section>

			<section id='installing-samba'>
				<title>Installing the Samba module</title>
				<para>
				FIXME magnetic
				</para>
			</section>

		</section>

	</section>

</chapter>
